George Cruikshank Collection
George Cruikshank Collection
1819-1866
Cruikshank, George, 1792-1878.
0.25 linear ft.
Papers of the British artist, caricaturist, illustrator, engraver. The collection contains 4 letters and 9 pieces of artwork.
148919
Biographical History
George Cruikshank was a British caricaturist, illustrator and engraver.
George Cruikshank was born in Bloomsbury, England in 1792. Cruikshank was taught art by his father, Isaac Cruikshank who was a caricaturist.
Cruikshank was influenced by English political cartoonist, James Gillray and Cruikshank finished several of Gillray’s pieces that were left unfinished at the time of his death in 1815. Several years later in 1820, Cruikshank received attention for his caricatures of Queen Caroline’s trial. Cruikshank regularly criticized what he saw as problems of contemporary society including the slave trade, the criminal code as well as French fashion and the French lifestyle in the work, Life in Paris (printed for John. Fairburn, 1822).
Cruikshank contributed to magazines such as Bentley's Miscellany and Ainsworth's Magazine and founded Wits. He also illustrated several books including Charles Dickens’ Oliver Twist (1838). In the 1840s, Cruikshank became active with the Temperance movement and illustrated materials promoting this campaign.
George Cruikshank died in 1878.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Cruikshank collection consists of two series: Artwork and Correspondence. Many of the items bear Cruikshank's signature. Artwork consists of sketches and finished engravings. Subject matter includes animals, mountains, the African Coast, streetscapes, and human figures. Correspondence contains four handwritten letters, two of which are dated. The letters are brief, one being more of a receipt than a piece of correspondence while another appears to be a short note offering sympathy.
Arrangement of the Collection
Each item is foldered individually.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists and illustrators. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Cruikshank, George, 1792-1878.; Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Illustrators; Animals in art.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Great Britain.; Cartoonists -- Great Britain.; Engravers -- Great Britain.; Etchers -- Great Britain.; Illustrators -- Great Britain.; Mountains in art.; Atlantic Coast (Africa) -- In Art.; London (England) -- In Art.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Engravings (prints); Sketches.; Artists.; Engravers.; Etchers.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Frank Piskor, 1968.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - "To Calais" engraving, 1 Aug 1835; depicts men and women on a boat; published by Thomas McLean, Haymarket; black and white (Box 1)
  - "From the West Indies" engraving, 1 Aug 1835; depicts men and women on a boat; published by Thomas McLean, Haymarket; black and white (Box 1)
  - "The British Bee Hive" sketch, undated; pencil and colored pencil (Box 1)
  - Camels, elephants, human figure, sketch, undated (Box 1)
  - "The Coast of Africa" sketch, undated; pencil, colored pencil (Box 1)
  - Female- nude sketch, undated; on the back of an envelope postmarked in London, also has writing (Box 1)
  - Mountains, sketch, circa Mar 1866; pencil and watercolor, has writing by Cruikshank, drawn on the back of a piece of letterhead for engraver W. Keningale (Box 1)
  - "Smoak Jack the Alarmist, Extinguishing the Second Great Fire of London (a la Gulliver), 12 Oct 1819; ink and watercolor, published by T Tegg No. 111, Cheanside (Box 1)
  - Street scene and carriages, undated; pencil, drawn on a list and schedule (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Letter to Charles Mottram, English engraver, 3 Oct 1863 (Box 1)
  - Letter to Charles A. Howell, 2 Nov 1866 (Box 1)
  - Letter to unknown recipient regarding a manuscript, undated (Box 1)
  - Letter to Sleap, undated; dated "Tuesday", appears to be regarding a death (Box 1)